我們將繁星摘下
We pulled the stars from the skies...
用來裝點地球
...and brought them down to Earth.
代價是什麼呢
But at what cost?
當我們點亮所有的燈同時
When we turned on all these lights...
也失去了一些寶貴的東西
we lost something precious.
繁星
The stars.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第八集
很久以前 只靠火光照亮
A long time ago, in a world lit only by fire,
我們和繁星之間的關係
our relationship with the stars
非常的
was far more...
貼心
personal.
幾千代人以來
For thousands of generations,
我們將繁星視作生活不可或缺的部分
we watched the stars as if our lives depended on it.
確實如此
Because they did.
我們人類不算最大
We humans were not the biggest, the strongest,
也不是最強壯或者最快的相比其他動物而言
nor the fastest of all the animals we competed against.
但我們有個特長
But we did have one thing going for us...
我們的智慧
our intelligence.
其中一點就是識別圖形的天賦
One aspect of that was a genius for pattern recognition
夜復一夜 我們仰望星空
Night after night, we watched the stars.
我們的祖先慢慢地注意到
And over time, our ancestors noticed
夜空中星星的移動預示著地球上的變化
that the motions of the stars across the nights of the year foretold changes on Earth
威脅或者增加我們生存的機會
that threatened or enhanced our chances for survival.
在我們只能依靠想像力來體會故事的年代
In a time when our imaginations were the only stage where stories came to life,
那時沒有電影或者電視
before there were movies or TVs
也沒有其他的電子設備
or electronic devices of any kind,
不同的文明將這些點連成各自不同的圖案
every human culture connected the dots to form their own pictures.
這些圖案變成故事書中的插圖
These images became the illustrations of a storybook
更深層面說來 也是一本生存手冊
that, on a deeper level, was also a survival manual.
天神和英雄們的名字個性
The names and personalities of the gods, heroes,
還有動物或者類似物體的名字和個性
farm animals or familiar objects
在各個文化中各不相同
varied from culture to culture.
除了一組特定的美麗星團
But there was one particularly gorgeous group of stars
從古希臘人到現在的我們都叫它
known to the Ancient Greeks and to us today
昴宿星團
as the Pleiades,
其位於金牛座 裸眼就可以輕易的看見 肉眼通常見到有六顆亮星
大約1億年前形成的星團
a star cluster formed about 100 million years ago.
每顆星都比太陽明亮40倍左右
Each of them is some 40 times brighter than our Sun.
昴宿六是最亮的一顆
And Alcyone, the most luminous,
比太陽亮1000倍
outshines our Sun 1,000 times.
以前昂宿星團被用來檢測視力
For ages, the Pleiades have been used as an eye test
而且世界通用
for people all over the world.
能看到6顆
If you could see at least six of them,
就是普通人的標準
you were considered normal.
看到超過7顆
If you saw more than seven,
就符合戰士或者偵察兵的標準了
you were an ideal candidate for a warrior or scout.
對於古凱爾特人和不列顛群島的德魯伊特來說
Among the Ancient Celts and Druids of the British Isles,
他們相信昂宿星團和亡魂有關
the Pleiades were believed to have a haunting significance.
一年中它們升到天空最高點的那一晚的午夜
On the night of the year that they reach the highest point in the sky at midnight,
亡魂會在地球上遊蕩
the spirits of the dead were thought to wander the Earth.
據信這是一個節日的起源
This is believed to be the origin of the holiday
以前叫薩溫節
once known as Samhain,
現在叫萬聖節
now called Halloween.
在世界各地 我們的祖先用
All over the Earth, our ancestors told
各種神奇的故事
wonderful stories to explain
來解釋昂宿星團的來歷
how the Pleiades came to be in the sky.
以北美洲的基奧瓦人來說
For the Kiowa people of North America,
故事是這樣的
it happened something like this.
很久很久以前 一些小姑娘
Long, long ago, some young women
溜出他們的營地
snuck away from their campsite
在星空下無拘無束的跳舞
to dance freely beneath the stars.
山神 救命啊
Rock, save us!
山神 可憐可憐我們吧
Rock, take pity on us!
山神聽到了她們的哭聲 升起了一座高高的山峰
The rock heard their cries and grew taller.
變成了今天的魔鬼峰
Until it became what is today known as the Devil's Tower.
這些姑娘變成了昂宿星團的星星
The maidens were transformed into the stars of the Pleiades,
冬至的時候可以看到她們高高的掛在山峰上
which may be seen hanging above the tower in midwinter.
古希臘人也將這7顆明珠
The Ancient Greeks also saw those seven jewels
看做7位少女
as seven maidens,
阿特拉斯的7個女兒
the seven daughters of Atlas,
負責以肩頂天的神
指的是獵戶座的那個獵戶
不是被熊追 而是被俄裏翁追
pursued not by bears, but by...Orion the hunter
他出來溜達的時候看到了她們
who spied them when he was out walking one day.
俄裏翁這個獵戶獸性大發
Orion became mad with desire.
追了她們7年 直到有一天
For seven years, he chased them relentlessly.
終於精疲力盡了 -宙斯 救命啊
- Exhausted... - Zeus, help us.
她們向宙斯呼救
...they prayed to Zeus for deliverance.
眾神之王宙斯大發慈悲
Zeus, the king of the gods, felt sorry for them,
把她們7個
and transformed those seven maidens
變成了昂宿星團
into the Pleiades.
但是 神就是神經病
But the gods are, if anything, capricious.
俄裏翁被蝎子蟄死後
When Orion was killed by the sting of a scorpion,
宙斯把他放在上天 讓他可以繼續追逐這7位姐妹
Zeus placed him in the sky where he could resume his pursuit of the seven gorgeous sisters
我們的祖先編織了各種美麗的傳說
Our ancestors, they wove brilliantly imaginative stories
但是除了想像 並不能讓我們更接近這些星星
But they can bring us no closer to the stars than our dreams
直到很多年後
It took yet another few thousand years
才有3位聰明的科學家揭開了這些星星的神秘面紗
until three brilliant scientists unlocked the secrets of the true lives of the stars
1901年
In 1901,
哈佛是男人的天下
Harvard was a man's world.
直到一位名叫愛德華·查爾斯·皮克林的天文學家
But an astronomer named Edward Charles Pickering
打破了這個規矩
broke that rule.
噢 皮克林的辦公室就在走廊盡頭
Oh, Pickering's office is just down the hallway.
那扇門的後面
And that door over there leads to the room
就是他的機房
where he keeps his computers.
說起來 這些女人都是「計算機」 但是
We're supposed to call those women "computers," but, uh,
我聽到不少人叫她們
I've heard more than one fellow refer to those gals
皮克林的後宮
as "Pickering's Harem."
皮克林招募了一群婦女
Pickering assembled a team of women
給星星分類 繪製星圖
to map and classify the types of stars.
其中一位為我們瞭解恆星的物質提供了
One of them provided the key to our understanding
關鍵的鑰匙
of the substance of the stars.
還有一位給我們提供了計算
And another devised a way for us to calculate
宇宙體積的方法
the size of the universe.
你可能從沒聽說過她們
For some reason, you probably never heard of either of them.
想知道原因嗎
Wonder why.
這個小組的組長名叫安妮·坎農
That's Annie Jump Cannon, the leader of the team.
完成時
Before she was through,
她分類了25萬顆恆星
she catalogued a quarter of a million stars.
11號是一顆B7星
Number 11 is a B7.
那是昂宿星團的昂宿六
That's Alcyone in the Pleiades.
在坎農還年輕的時候
Cannon lost her hearing during a bout of scarlet fever
她不幸因為感染猩紅熱而喪失了聽力
when she was a young woman.
12號是一顆B6星
Number 12 is a B6.
那是亨麗愛塔·勒維特 也是失聰
That's Henrietta Swan Leavitt. She's also deaf.
她是這裏的另一位偉大的科學家
And she's the other great scientist in the room.
勒維特發明了天文學家沿用上百年的方法
Leavitt discovered the law that astronomers still use more than a century later
用來測量恆星之間的距離
to measure the distances to the stars
還有宇宙的體積
and the size of the cosmos itself.
安妮·坎農在一張賀卡中說明了
Annie Jump Cannon sent out a Christmas card explaining
她們正在從事的工作
what she and her sisters were actually doing.
恆星發出的光可以
The light from a star is allowed
通過望遠鏡中的棱鏡 她寫道
to fall through a prism placed in the telescope, she wrote.
經過放大 星光可以分解成一組色帶
Thus magnified, the starlight is split up into a band
顯示出組成的顏色
showing its component colors,
紅光和紫光分別處於兩端
the red rays going to one end and the violet to the other.
這就是恆星的光譜
This is the spectrum of the star.
由深色細線表示
It shows the presence of fine, dark lines.
將這些細線與實驗室中發光物質做對比
By comparing them with lines given by glowing substances in the laboratory
我們可以斷定這些地球上熟悉的物質
we can determine that the same elements familiar to us
同樣存在於遙遠的恆星上
on the Earth also exist in the outermost star.
這是12358B號
This is plate number 12358B.
這塊板上的第一號是顆B類星
Number one at this plate is a B-type star.
定為B2
Make that a B2.
坎農用了幾十年
It took Cannon decades
按照光譜特性
to classify the spectral character
為成千上萬的恆星分門別類
of hundreds of thousands of stars
根據她制定的方法
according to the scheme that she devised.
坎農認為恆星可以
Cannon discovered that the stars fell
根據它們的光譜線圖被分為7大類
into a continuous sequence of seven broad categories according to their spectral line patterns.
每個大類由一個字母代表
Each was designated by a letter.
但是相同類別的兩顆恆星的光譜線
But the spectral lines of two stars in the same letter class
可能有著細微的區別
could differ in subtle ways,
坎農根據記憶察覺到的細微變化
minute variations that Cannon learned to recognize from memory.
為了區分這些光譜
To distinguish these spectra from one another,
她又將每大類分為10個用數字代表的小類
she assigned ten numerical subcategories for each class.
安妮·坎農將恆星歸類
Annie Jump Cannon organized the stars,
另一位科學家負責解密她的成果中隱藏的含義
but it would fall to another scientist to decipher the hidden meaning in her work
1923年的英格蘭 婦女無權
In the England of 1923, women were forbidden
在科學上獲得高級學位
from pursuing advanced degrees in science.
但是塞西莉亞·佩恩在倫敦參加了一個講座
But Cecelia Payne had attended a lecture in London
由亞瑟·愛丁頓爵士演講
by the astronomer Sir Arthur Eddington,
他是首位證實
the first scientist to provide evidence
愛因斯坦廣義相對論的科學家
that Einstein's revolutionary General Theory of Relativity was correct.
從那時起
From that moment on,
她知道沒什麼可以阻擋她
she knew that nothing would deter her
追求她的夢想
from pursing her big dreams.
她決定移居美國
She resolved to emigrate to America,
在那裏婦女已經有了研究恆星的自由
where women had already gained the freedom to study the stars.
哈佛大學接受了她的申請
Her application was accepted at Harvard.
她隨後的發現改變了一個天文學的基本觀點
What she would discover there would challenge one of the central beliefs of astronomy.
造成的影響就如同現代天文物理學的曙光
The resulting impact would be the dawn of modern astrophysics.
幾十年過去了
As the decades passed,
安妮·坎農和她的組員不斷地篩分恆星
Annie Jump Cannon and her team kept sifting the stars,
檢查每一顆的光譜特徵
checking each one's spectral signature
並將它們歸入
with a fleeting glance and then dropping them
7大分類中
into one of seven categories.
它們變成了圖片中成千上萬的像素
They became hundreds of thousands of dots
在當時還沒人能夠瞭解它的含義
in a larger picture which no one could yet understand.
這支隊伍中又來了一位新的成員
Into this community of women came one more.
哈嘍
Well, hello there.
你就是佩恩吧
You must be Miss Payne.
等你好久啦
We've been waiting for you.
快進來
Come on in.
塞西莉亞·佩恩第一次在科研環境中受到這樣的歡迎
Cecilia Payne had never experienced such kindness in a scientific setting before.
姐妹們無私的與她分享研究成果
This sisterhood generously shared the fruits of their labors with her,
她將她們的觀察結果
and she turned their observations
轉化成一種對恆星的全新認識
into a radical new understanding of the stars.
兩個女人變成了非常要好的朋友
The two women became great friends.
坎農把恆星光譜對佩恩傾囊相授
Cannon taught Payne everything she had learned about stellar spectra
佩恩著手分析坎農的數據
And Payne began to analyze Cannon's data
嘗試著判斷恆星中的化學成分與物理狀態
to see if she could determine the actual chemical composition and physical state of the stars
她發揮了她的理論原子物理學專長
She brought to this work her expertise in theoretical and atomic physics
恆星光譜中最突出的特徵
The most prominent features in the spectra of stars
顯示了重金屬元素的存在 比如鈣 和鐵
showed the presence of heavy elements such as calcium... and iron,
地球上最常見的那些元素
which are among the most abundant elements in the Earth.
天文學家自然而然的得出結論
So astronomers naturally concluded
恆星是由與地球相同的物質組成
that the stars were made of the same elements as the Earth
就連比例都大致相同
and in roughly the same proportions.
1924年 當時的美國天文學泰斗亨利·諾利斯·羅素
In 1924, Henry Norris Russell was the dean
為我們對於恆星的瞭解做出了重大的貢獻
of American astronomers having made major contributions to our understanding of the stars.
地球上的40到45號化學元素
40 to 45 of the chemical elements that we have here on Earth
一樣存在與太陽的光譜中
are also present in the spectrum of the Sun.
所以我們可以推斷太陽的成分
So we can assume that the composition of the Sun
與地球類似
resembles that of the Earth.
如果有人能把地殼加熱到發出光芒
If one were to heat the crust of the Earth to incandescence,
它的光譜就會和太陽類似
its spectrum would resemble that of the Sun.
安妮 我明白了這麼多年來你的工作成果的真正意義
Annie, I think I now understand what it all means. All your years of work.
說來聽聽
Tell me.
我計算了不同溫度下的光譜
I've calculated what the spectra should look like across a wide range of temperatures,
它們和你的分類法完美吻合
and they match your system of classification perfectly
恆星的光譜可以表示它的溫度
The spectrum of any star tells you exactly how hot it is.
你的OBAFGKM就是恆星的溫標
Your "O-B-A-F-G-K-M" is really a temperature scale of the stars
OBAFGKM=哈佛分類法 各個字母代表不同的光譜類別
從最熱到最冷
from the hottest to the coldest.
重點來了 安妮 多虧了你
Here's the headline, Annie. Thanks to your work,
我發現 恆星幾乎全部是由氫和氦組成
I've discovered that the stars are made almost entirely of hydrogen and helium.
恆星中的氫和氦比金屬多上百萬倍
There's a million times more hydrogen and helium than the metals in the stars
我知道聽上去好像挺傻
I know, it sounds daft.
你確定嗎
Are you certain?
有人核對過你的計算結果嗎
Has anyone else checked your calculations?
還沒 我都寫進我的論文裏了
Not yet, but it's all in my thesis,
已經寄給羅素教授了
which is already on its way to Professor Russell.
倒霉孩子
Poor woman.
羅素對她表示遺憾
Russell felt sorry for Cecilia Payne.
在他看來 她的論文從根本上就是錯的
Her thesis appeared to him to be fundamentally flawed.
顯然氫和氦不可能比金屬多上百萬倍
It is clearly impossible that hydrogen should be a million times more abundant than the metals.
她仔細收集的證據與傳統的科學觀點不相符
Her carefully gathered evidence flew in the face of conventional scientific wisdom.
我怎麼可能是對的 她問
"How could I be right," she asked,
那就意味著
"if that must mean
那麼著名的科學家錯了
that such a distinguished scientist was wrong?"
儘管她對自己的研究結果很自信
Despite her confidence in the quality of her research,
她還是在她的論文裏加上了一句 「高的幾乎可以肯定不真實」
she caved and added a sentence to her thesis
動搖了這個非常偉大的觀點
that undermined its greatest insight.
4年後
It would be four years
羅素才意識到佩恩是正確的
before Russell realized that Payne was right.
值得表揚的是 他一認識到這點
To his credit, as soon as he did,
他就承認了 這是佩恩的發現
he acknowledged that it was her discovery.
佩恩的《恆星大氣》被普遍看做是
Payne's "Stellar Atmospheres" is widely regarded
天文學有史以來最傑出的博士論文
as the most brilliant PhD thesis ever written in astronomy.
它成了這個領域裏教科書
It became the standard text in its field.
沒有堅持我的觀點是我的責任
I was to blame for not having pressed my point.
儘管我相信自己的正確 卻還是屈服於權威
I had given in to authority when I believed I was right.
如果你對自己的結論有把握
If you are sure of your facts,
你就應該堅持你的立場
you should defend your position.
恆星大氣學
在其他領域 權威的言論可能佔優勢
The words of the powerful may prevail in other spheres of human experience
但對科學來說 最關鍵的是證據
but in science, the only thing that counts is the evidence
以及爭議本身的邏輯性
and the logic of the argument itself.
佩恩解釋了安妮坎農的恆星光譜序列
Cecilia Payne's interpretation of Annie Jump Cannon's sequence
使我們可以理解恆星生命的故事
of stellar spectra made it possible for us to read the life stories of the stars
並且根據這個從它燃燒的終點追溯回它的起源
and to trace the story of life itself back to its beginnings in their fiery deaths.
有很多種恆星
There are many kinds of stars.
一些像太陽般明亮
Some are bright like the Sun.
有些暗淡
Some are dim.
最大的恆星比最小的要大上千萬倍
The greatest stars are ten million
times larger than the smallest ones
有些恆星古老的超出想像
Some stars are old beyond imagining,
超過100億歲
more than ten billion years of age.
有些才剛剛誕生
Others are being born right now.
當原子在恆星的核心中融合
When atoms fuse in the hearts of stars,
它們發出星光
they make starlight.
恆星從雜物中誕生
Stars are born in litters,
由星際雲的氣體和灰塵組成
formed from the gas and dust of interstellar clouds.
不同恆星的質量差異
The mass of the individual stars in a litter
從小的那些 並不比最大的行星大多少
can range from the runts--not much larger than the largest planets--
到大的那些超巨星 讓太陽都相形見絀
to the supergiant stars that dwarf the Sun.
獵戶座腰帶下方星雲中的恆星剛剛誕生
The stars in the nebula below Orion's Belt are newborns,
差不多500萬歲
around five million years old,
還被包裹在誕生時的氣體和灰塵中
and still swaddled in the gas and dust that gave birth to them.
昂宿星團中的恆星已經到了蹣跚學步的年紀
The stars in the Pleiades are already toddlers,
1億歲左右
about 100 million years old.
它們已經甩開了氣體和灰塵的遮蓋
They've shed their blankets of gas and dust,
但依然被彼此的引力束縛在一起
but they're still bound together by their mutual gravity.
再過幾億年
Another few hundred million years,
它們才會各奔東西
and they'll drift apart and go their separate ways,
從此再不相見
never to meet again.
北斗星中的大部分恆星已經是青少年了
Most of the stars of the Big Dipper are adolescents,
5億歲左右
roughly half a billion years old.
它們已經離開了出生時的星團
They've already drifted apart from their birth cluster,
不過 我們還是能找到它們共同的祖先
although we can still trace their common ancestry.
最終 它們會散落在銀河系中
Eventually, they'll spread out around the Milky Way galaxy.
但是大部分常見的星座
But most of the familiar constellations
是由完全不相關的恆星混合而成
are a mix of entirely unrelated stars,
有些暗淡而相距不遠
some faint and nearby,
有些明亮遠遠相隔
others bright and far away.
我們的太陽呢
Our own Sun?
從幾光年開外看去 也很難找到其他相近的恆星
From the distance of even a few light-years, it's hard to find amidst the other stars.
那個
It's that one.
我們的太陽已進中年
Our Sun is middle-aged
離開出生地也很遠了
and a long way from where it was born.
從同一個星際雲誕生的姐妹星們
Its sister stars hatched from the same interstellar cloud,
分散在銀河系各處
are dispersed throughout the galaxy.
許多都有它們各自的行星
Many of them have their own planets.
或許有些已經孕育了
Perhaps some of them nurture
智慧生物和生命的進化
the evolution of life and intelligence.
夜空中的大多數恆星
Most of the stars in our night sky
會環繞一個或多個恆星小夥伴運行
actually orbit around one or more stellar companions.
在這種雙星或者多星的系統內 靠我們的肉眼
With the naked eye, we usually can't see the fainter members
通常看不到較暗的那些星
in such double and multiple star systems.
在有3個太陽的世界裏
On a world with three suns,
很少有夜晚
the nights would be rare
白天也在紅色和藍色中交替
and the days might alternate between red and blue.
恆星的坍縮是注定的
It is the destiny of stars to collapse.
抬頭看向夜空 所看到的成千上萬的星星
Of the thousands of stars you see when you look up at the night sky,
每一個都活在兩次坍縮之間
every one of them is living in an interval between two collapses...
黑暗的星際氣體雲團的第一次坍縮
an initial collapse of a dark, interstellar gas cloud
形成了恆星
to form the star,
明亮恆星的最後一次坍縮
and a final collapse of the luminous star
是它的生命盡頭
on its way to its ultimate fate.
沒有外力干擾的情況下 引力使恆星收縮
Gravity makes stars contract, unless some other force intervenes
太陽是個熾熱氣體組成的大球體
The Sun is a great, big ball of incandescent gas.
核心的超高溫氣體
The super hot gas in its core
促使太陽向外擴張
pushes the Sun to expand outward.
與此同時 太陽的引力
At the same time,the Sun's own gravity
又使它向內收縮
pulls it inward to contract.
我們的太陽處在兩種力穩定平衡的狀態
And our Sun is poised between these two forces in a stable equilibrium
引力和核爆炸
between gravity and nuclear fire,
這種平衡會繼續
a balance it will maintain
保持40億年
for another four billion years.
太陽消耗氫氣
But as the Sun consumes hydrogen,
它的核心慢慢的收縮
its core very slowly shrinks,
而它的表面卻在逐步的擴張
and the Sun's surface gradually expands in response.
在幾百萬年的時間裏 過程很緩慢 不易察覺
It happens very slowly,imperceptibly, over the course of millions of years
但對於10億年來說
But in about a billion years,
太陽會比現在亮出百分之10
the Sun will be ten percent brighter than it is today
百分之10 聽上去不多
Ten percent may not sound like much,
但這些額外的熱量會對地球造成很大的影響
but that extra heat will have a big effect on Earth.
當太陽最終耗盡它的核燃料
When the Sun finally exhausts its nuclear fuel
40或者50億年後
four or five billion years from now,
氣體會冷卻 壓力會下降
its gas will cool and the pressure will fall.
太陽的內部無法繼續支撐外層的重量
The Sun's interior can no longer support the weight of the outer layers
最初的坍縮再次繼續
and the initial collapse will resume.
萬物都沒有永恆
Nothing lasts forever.
恆星也會死
Even the stars die.
氦 100億年來氫聚變的灰燼
Helium, the ash of ten billion years of hydrogen fusion,
在核心中匯聚
has built up in the core.
沒有核爆炸支持它的重量
With no nuclear fire to sustain its weight,
內核坍縮 溫度高的開始將氦聚合成碳和氧
the core collapses until it becomes hot enough to start fusing helium into carbon and oxygen
太陽內核的溫度比以前高很多
The core of the Sun is now much hotter than it was before.
它的大氣急劇膨脹
Its atmosphere rapidly expands.
在接下來的10億年裏 它膨脹到
Over the next billion years, it'll become bloated
超過現在體積的100倍
to more than 100 times its original size
變成一顆紅巨星
a red giant star.
它將會覆蓋併吞噬
It will envelop and devour
水星
the planets Mercury...
金星
...and Venus...
很可能還有地球
...and possibly the Earth.
我認為
I like to think that
在那之前的幾千萬年
tens of millions of years before that far distant future,
如果地球上還有生命誕生
if there still be life born of Earth,
它們應該已經在其他星球找到了新家
it will have found new homes among the stars.
一旦太陽燃盡所有的氦
Once the Sun burns through its helium,
它就開始變得非常不穩定
it will become highly unstable,
將它的外圍甩向太空
casting off its outer layers into space.
超級炙熱的裸露核心
The exposed, super hot core
發出高能量的紫外線 潮水般淹沒四周
will flood its surroundings with high-energy ultraviolet light.
原子們發著光 瘋狂的劇烈活動
The atoms will perform a wild, fluorescent dance.
太陽會像蛋奶酥一樣的收縮塌陷
The Sun will collapse like a souffle
縮小到地球體積的幾百倍
shrinking a hundredfold to the size of the Earth.
到那時 太陽極度緊密 過度擁擠的電子開始相互排擠
And at that point, the Sun will be so dense that its overcrowded electrons will push back,
一切收縮都停止了
stopping any further contraction.
只有太陽中心的光核還依然堅持在那裏
The kernel of light at the center will be the only part of the Sun that endures
變成了白矮星 它還會繼續發出微弱的光
a white dwarf star that will go on shining dimly
再持續1千億年
for another 100 billion years.
遙遠未來的生命
Will the beings of a distant future,
從這顆星的殘骸旁路過
sailing past this wreck of a star,
會想到它曾經照耀過得那些生命和世界嗎
have any idea of the life and worlds that it once warmed?
普通恆星死亡時的炫目光罩轉瞬即逝
The psychedelic death shrouds of ordinary stars are fleeting,
只會延續幾萬年的時間
lasting only tens of thousands of years
然後消散成星際氣體和灰塵
before dissipating in the interstellar gas and dust
新的恆星又會從中誕生
from which the new stars will be born.
聯星系統中的恆星
The stars in a binary star system
可以有不一樣的命運
can have a different fate.
天狼星 夜空中最亮那顆星
Sirius, the brightest star in the night sky,
有一個非常暗淡的伴隨者
has a very faint stellar companion--
一顆白矮星
a white dwarf.
曾經像太陽一樣
It was once a Sun-like star.
有一天 天狼星耗盡了燃料
Someday, when Sirius runs out of fuel
變成了紅巨星
and becomes a red giant,
它的物質會流向白矮星
it will shed its substance onto the white dwarf.
這位伴隨者的強大引力會吸引氣體
The intense gravity of the companion will attract that gas,
使它們形成一個螺旋狀的圓盤
pulling it into a spiraling disk.
從較大恆星出來的氣體
When the gas from the larger star
落在白矮星的表面
falls onto the surface of the white dwarf,
引發核爆炸
it will trigger nuclear explosions.
最大規模的爆炸會釋放
The greatest burst will release
超過太陽10萬倍的能量
100,000 times more energy than the Sun.
每一次的爆炸被稱為 新星
Each one of those star bursts is called a "nova,"
Nova：新星
在拉丁語中就是 新 的意思
from the Latin for "new."
一顆質量相當於15個太陽的恆星
A star about 15 times as massive as the Sun,
比如參宿七 一顆藍超巨星
one like Rigel, the blue supergiant
獵戶座的右腳
that forms the right foot of Orion,
就有著不同的命運
has a different fate in store.
電子的壓力不會使它的坍縮停止
Its collapse will not be stopped by the pressure of electrons.
它持續坍縮
The star will keep falling in on itself,
直到原子核過度擁擠
until its nuclei become so overcrowded
開始相互排斥
that they push back.
參宿七會縮小差不多10萬倍
Rigel will shrink down about 100,000 times,
直到原子核之間沒有距離
until there's no space left between the nuclei
無法再縮小
and it can shrink no more.
到那時 它引發
At that point, it ignites
一場更強烈的核反應 超新星
a more powerful nuclear reaction, a supernova.
大部分的恆星演變
Most stellar evolution
要經歷幾百萬或者幾十億年
takes millions or billions of years.
但是內部的坍縮
But the interior collapse
引發超新星爆炸只需要幾秒鐘
that triggers a supernova explosion takes only seconds.
只剩下一個原子核
What remains will be an atomic nucleus
一個小城市那麼大
the size of a small city--
急速旋轉的中子星被稱為 脈衝星
a rapidly rotating neutron star called a pulsar.
但對於質量超過太陽30倍的恆星
But for a star more than 30 times as massive as the Sun--
比如參宿二 在獵戶座的腰帶上
a star like Alnilam, in Orion's Belt--
沒什麼可以阻止它的坍縮
there will be no stopping its collapse.
幾百萬年後
In a few million years,
參宿二燃燒殆盡
when Alnilam runs out of fuel,
它也會變成超新星
it, too, will go supernova.
崩潰的參宿二核心
The imploding core of Alnilam
質量大得 即使核力也不足以承受它的坍縮
will be so massive that not even nuclear forces
will be strong enough to hold off its collapse.
沒有什麼可以抵抗這種引力
Nothing can withstand such gravity.
密度如此驚人的恆星
And such a star has an astonishing destiny.
它會持續坍縮
It will continues to collapse,
超越時空的界限
crossing a boundary in space-time
稱為 視界
called the "event horizon,"
即黑洞表面
我們無法看到內部
beyond which we cannot see.
當它貫穿那個界限
When it traverses that frontier,
星星從我們的視線 消失得無影無蹤
the star will vanish completely from sight.
它在黑洞內
It will be inside a black hole,
那裏的引力無比強大 即使光也無法逃脫
a place where gravity is so strong that nothing, not even light, can escape.
還有一種罕見的恆星有著更戲劇化的命運
But there's an even more dramatic fate that awaits a rare kind of star
我們的銀河系就有一顆
There's one of them in our galaxy.
它很不穩定 當它爆炸時
It's so unstable that when it goes,
它不會變成新星或者超新星
it won't become a mere nova or supernova.
它變成更大的災難
It'll become something far more catastrophic...
極超新星
a hypernova.
在我們這輩子就可能發生
And it could happen in our lifetime.
澳洲內陸是地球上最好的星空觀測地點之一
There are few places on Earth to get a better view of the night sky than the Australian Outback.
沒有建築物
No buildings,
沒車 沒路燈 什麼都沒有
no cars, streetlights, nothing out here;
只有星光
just lots of starlight...
偶爾有幾隻袋鼠
and the occasional kangaroo.
在這裏 你可以非常好的觀察銀河系
You can get a particularly good view of the Milky Way from down here.
銀河的中心
The center of our galaxy
高懸在空中
rises high in the sky,
拱形穿過天空
and it arches across the heavens
就像黑夜的脊樑
like the backbone of night.
我們的銀河系是個螺旋星雲
We live in a spiral galaxy.
我們看向銀河時
And when we look at the Milky Way,
我們可以看到螺旋圓盤中幾十億顆恆星發出的光
we're seeing light from billions of stars in its spiral disk.
在這樣美麗的夜空下
And under this beautiful dark sky,
你能看到銀河並不是一片明亮
you can see that the Milky Way isn't a uniform band of light.
有些黑色的斑塊遮掩了星光
There are dark patches, breaks in the starlight.
那些黑色的斑塊就是星際塵埃
Those dark patches are caused by interstellar dust.
數量眾多的塵埃阻擋了星光
The dust blocks the starlight, and there's lots of it.
大部分的文明中 將星星相連
Most cultures looked up at the stars and connected the dots
在夜空中組成熟悉的圖案
to form familiar images in the sky.
星座
Constellations.
但是澳洲土著
But the Aboriginal people of Australia
注意到了黑影的形狀
saw a pattern in the darkness
貫穿銀河
running through the Milky Way.
看上去像鴯鹋 一種大鳥 一種澳洲大陸本土動物
They saw an emu, a large bird native to this continent.
它並不是由星星組成 而是在沒有星星的地方悄然出現
Not in the stars,but in the absence of stars.
有不用的方式來看星空
There are so many ways to look at the night sky.
上百萬年的時間裏
For a million years or more, we've watched the sky.
發生了很多事
And a lot's happened in that time.
我們的銀河系中超新星爆炸大約100年一次
Supernova explode in our galaxy about once a century.
如果我們把所有遙望星空的夜晚壓縮成一分鐘
If we could compress all those nights of stargazing into a single minute
這是我們可以看到的景象
this is what we would see.
如果把我們的眼睛比做望遠鏡
Now, if our eyes were telescopes,
口徑和車輪一樣大
if they were light buckets as big as wagon wheels
我們又可以識別不僅僅一種光時
and our vision was not limited to just one kind of light,
我們看到的銀河系就是這樣的
then this is the Milky Way we would see.
近紅外光中的星系
A galaxy in near-infrared light
觸手般四處蔓延的塵埃
with streaming tendrils of dust
被爆炸的超新星猛烈地甩出
hurled outward by those exploding supernovas,
在無數星星的映襯下顯現出來
silhouetted against a backdrop of countless stars
大約7500光年以外
About 7,500 light-years away,
銀河系的另一端
in another part of our galaxy,
有一場巨變
there is a place of upheaval
規模大得難以想像
on an inconceivable scale.
這是船底座星雲
This is the Carina Nebula.
一台恆星製造機
A star-making machine.
光線要用50年的時間才能貫穿
It takes a ray of light 50 years to cross it.
巨大的恆星在這裏誕生
The titanic stars born here
強烈的紫外線輻射烤焦了周圍的氣體和塵埃
sear the surrounding gas and dust with their fierce ultraviolet radiation.
巨大的恆星死亡時
When a massive star dies,
將它自己炸成碎片
it blows itself to smithereens.
它的物質被推得四處紛飛
Its substance is propelled across the vastness
被星光攪動
to be stirred by starlight
被引力匯聚
and gathered up by gravity.
由恆星變成塵埃
Stars to dust
再由塵埃變為恆星
and dust to stars.
宇宙中 沒有廢物
In the cosmos, nothing is wasted.
但是恆星的質量有一個上限
But there's an upper limit to how massive a star can be.
17世紀時 愛德蒙·哈雷
Back in the 17th century, when Edmond Halley
跨過赤道 繪製南方的星座圖
crossed the equator to map the southern constellations,
海山二看上去只是一顆暗星
Eta Carinae seemed like just another faint star.
一個位於船底星座
但到了1843年 海山二
But in 1843, Eta Carinae
突然變成了天空中第二亮的星
suddenly became the second brightest star in the sky,
只是比天狼星稍暗
outshined only by Sirius.
從此開始爆發
And it's been flipping out ever since.
那個啞鈴形的雲團
That dumbbell-shaped cloud
就是爆發的膨脹殘餘
is the expanding remnant of that event.
中心是一顆瘋狂的恆星
At its center is one crazy star.
說到不穩定
Talk about unstable
海山二比太陽的質量大出至少100倍
Eta Carinae is at least 100 times more massive than the Sun,
並且發出比太陽多500萬倍的光
and pouring out five million times more light.
它一直在挑戰恆星質量的上限
It's pushing the upper limit of what a star can be.
還有 有證據顯示 海山二
What's more, there's evidence that Eta Carinae
飽受它那邪惡兄弟的重力折磨
is being gravitationally tormented by an evil twin--
那是一顆繞它運行的恆星
another massive star in orbit around it
之間的距離就像土星到太陽的距離
as close as Saturn is to the Sun.
超級巨大的恆星內核發出大量的光
The core of a supermassive star pours out so much light
以致向外的壓力蓋過了恆星的引力
that the outward pressure can overwhelm the star's gravity.
如果恆星過於巨大
If a star is too massive,
它的輻射壓力超過它的引力
its radiation pressure overpowers its gravity
就會將這顆星炸裂
and blows the star apart.
海山二的命運
The fate of Eta Carinae was sealed
在幾百萬年前誕生時就已經注定
when it was born millions of years ago.
當它最終爆炸時
When it finally does blow up
說不定 已經爆炸了
and who knows, maybe it already has;
畢竟 我們看到的光
after all, we're looking at it by light that left the star
是7500年前發出的
7,500 years ago--
那會是我們從沒見過的大災難
it will be a cataclysm unlike anything we've seen before.
極超新星
A hypernova.
爆炸威力大得使超新星看上去就如同鞭炮一樣
An explosion so powerful, it'll make a supernova seem like a firecracker by comparison.
如果附近有太陽系
If there are nearby solar systems
伴隨有生命的行星 它們的死期到了
with planets harboring life, their days are numbered.
極超新星噴出大量的輻射
A hypernova spews so much radiation into space--
不只光 還有X射線 伽馬射線
not just light, but X-rays and gamma rays--
幾十光年外的行星
that planets that are dozens
或者甚至幾百光年外的
or perhaps hundreds of light-years away
都會喪失它們的大氣層
could be stripped of their atmospheres
然後被死亡輻射籠罩
and bathed in deadly radiation.
它可以肆虐周圍幾千個恆星系統
It would wreak havoc in thousands of nearby star systems.
現在 你可能好奇
Right about now, you're probably asking yourself,
我們安全嗎
"Are we safe?"
如果海山二爆炸
If Eta Carinae blows up,
地球怎麼辦
what happens to Earth?
放心吧 地球不會有事
Rest assured, Earth will be just fine.
記住 我們離它7500光年呢
Remember, we're 7,500 light-years away from Eta Carinae.
恆星放出的輻射強度
The intensity of radiation from a star,
即使是一顆爆炸的恆星
even an exploding star,
隨著距離急劇下降
falls off rapidly with distance.
即使這樣 海山二的謝幕演出
But still, Eta Carinae in its death throes
依然會非常精彩
will put on quite a show.
它會點亮南半球的夜空
It will light up the night of the southern hemisphere
亮得如同月亮一樣
with the brightness of a second moon.
奉獻上最激動人心的告別演出
The most dramatic swan song a star can sing.
我們的祖先崇拜太陽
Our ancestors worshipped the Sun.
他們絕不是愚蠢
And they were far from foolish.
對太陽和恆星的崇拜很有道理
It makes good sense to revere the Sun and stars,
因為我們是它們的孩子
because we are their children.
岩石中的硅 空氣中的氧
The silicon in the rocks, the oxygen in the air,
DNA中的碳 摩天大樓中的鐵
the carbon in our DNA, the iron in our skyscrapers,
珠寶中的銀
the silver in our jewelry
都是恆星們幾十億年前創造的
were all made in stars billions of years ago.
我們的星球 我們的社會 還有我們自己
Our planet, our society and we ourselves
都是星塵
are stardust.
是什麼使原子們這麼活躍
Well, what is it that makes the atoms dance?
恆星的能量是如何轉變為
How is the energy of a star transformed
世界上所發生的一切呢
into everything that happens in the world?
什麼是能量
What is energy?
我們都身處其中
We're awash in it.
當氫原子在太陽中聚合
When hydrogen atoms fuse inside the Sun,
產生氦原子
they make helium atoms.
這種核聚變發出一股能量
And this fusion emits a burst of energy
可以在太陽內部遊蕩1千萬年
that can wander inside the Sun for ten million years
然後到達表面
before making its way to the surface.
然後獲得自由
And once there, it's free to fly
直接向地球飛來
straight from the Sun to the Earth
就是可見光
as visible light.
如果它撞擊在葉子的表面
If it should strike the surface of a leaf,
它就被作為化學能量保存在了地球
it will be stored in the plant as chemical energy.
日光
Sunshine...
變成月光
into moonshine.
這裏指的是一種威士忌
我能感受到我的大腦把葡萄酒的化學能量
I can feel my brain turning the chemical energy of the wine
轉變為思想的電能
into the electrical energy of my thoughts
指揮我的聲帶
and directing my vocal chords
產生我說話的聲能
to produce the acoustic energy of my voice.
這種能量的轉換
Such transformations of energy
無時無刻都在發生
are happening everywhere all the time.
太陽的能量
Energy from our star
驅動風和浪
drives the wind and the waves
還有我們四周的生命
and the life around us.
有這樣大量的清潔能源是多麼幸運的事情
How lucky we are to have this vast source of clean energy
這簡直是給所有人的天賜之物
falling like manna from heaven on all of us.
敬 安妮·坎農
To Annie Jump Cannon,
亨麗愛塔·勒維特
Henrietta Swan Leavitt
還有塞西莉亞·佩恩
and Cecilia Payne
感謝她們開創了現代天文物理學
for blazing the trail to modern astrophysics.
還要敬 太陽的所有姐妹們
And to all the sisters of the Sun.
宇宙中一切都逃不過改變
There's no refuge from change in the cosmos.
從現在以後的壹千萬或兩千萬年
Some ten or 20 million years from now,
在宇宙中只是片刻
it'll seem for a cosmic moment
彷彿獵戶俄裏翁終於要抓到七姐妹了
as if Orion is finally about to catch the seven sisters.
但在他抓住她們之前
But before he has them in his clutches,
獵戶座最大的幾顆恆星就會變成超新星
the biggest stars of Orion will go supernova.
獵戶座對昂宿星座的追趕會從此停止
Orion's pursuit of the Pleiades will finally end,
那七位姐妹
and the seven sisters
會緩緩地投入銀河系的臂彎
will glide serenely into the waiting arms of the Milky Way
我們在地球上對太陽升起發出贊嘆
We on Earth marvel and rightly so-- at the return of our solitary Sun.
在遙遠的球狀星雲中 從一個環繞恆星的行星上看
But from a planet orbiting a star in a distant globular cluster,
還能看到更多驚艷的黎明
a still more glorious dawn awaits.
不是太陽升起
Not a sunrise...
而是星系的升起
but a galaxy rise.
2千億顆太陽照耀的早晨
A morning filled with 200 billion suns.
銀河系的升起
The rising of the Milky Way.
巨大的螺旋狀伴隨者坍塌的氣體雲團
An enormous spiral form with collapsing gas clouds,
凝結的行星系統 發光的超巨星
condensing planetary systems, luminous supergiants,
穩定的中年太陽，紅巨星，白矮星
stable middle-aged suns, red giants, white dwarfs,
行星狀星雲 超新星
planetary nebulas, supernovas,
中子星 脈衝星 黑洞
neutron stars, pulsars, black holes
有充分的理由認為
and, there is every reason to think,
還有其他的天體 我們尚未發現
other exotic objects that we have yet to discover.
從這樣的一個世界 高懸於銀河系
From such a world, high above the Milky Way,
這麼的清晰 清晰地如同我們世界起源時
it would be clear, as it is beginning to be clear on our world,
我們由原子和眾星組成
that we are made by the atoms and the stars,
我們的物質 我們的形態
that our matter and our form
由偉大而古老的宇宙鍛造
are forged by the great and ancient cosmos,
我們也是這個宇宙的一部分
of which we are a part.
中文翻譯：@SaltyEggPain timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息